#大家好 今天來另外一個兄弟家
Hi everyone! Today we go to another brother's place,
#找一下 看一下他的公鼠夠不夠
to find, to see if they have enough male rats.
#我們家公鼠太缺啦
We need a lot more male rats.
#到處找 看一下找不找得到公鼠
We are going everywhere, trying to get some.
#現在都沒有公的 沒有公的給他們配種啦
We now have no more males, no more males for breeding.
#喵
Meow
#不是貓
They are not cats!
#哈哈哈 哈哈哈
Ha ha ha! Ha ha ha!
#哎喲 跑那麼快
Aiyo! They are running so fast.
#哇 這個是母的哦
Wa! This is a female.
#你看
See?
#這個都是白的
It is white here
#屁股都是黃的 這個黑的 黑的
the butt is brown, this is black, black.
#這個黑的 黑的
This is black, black.
#幹嘛 你看 它一直看著我
What's up? See? It is staring at me.
#想跟我握手
You want to shake hands with me,
#是不是
don't you?
#哇
Wa!
#那麼友好的 哦
You are so friendly, oh!
#它幹嘛兩個手抱在這裡
What does it mean? Its both hands are holding here.
#不敢動 是不是
You don't dare to move, do you?
#不要怕
Relax
#別怕 我只看看你而已呀
Relax! I just want to take a look at you,
#我只看一下你
just a look.
#哎喲
Aiyo!
#抓我一下
You clawed me.
#這個 白的
This is, white.
#這個是熊貓鼠一樣的哦
It's like a panda rat.
#你看
See?
#這兩邊
The two sides,
#這兩邊都是黑黑的
the two sides are black.
#這個鼻子是白的
The nose is white.
#它們的肚子上 全身都是白的
Their bellies and bodies are all white.
#第一下兄弟送一個給我
I'll ask my brother for one.
#去去 (按︰這應該是挑逗竹鼠的聲音而已)
Chu chu
#哇 你看 這個公的
Wa! See? This is a male.
#比我家的還累哦
It should be more tired than mine.
#1 2 3 4, 4 個母的
One two three four, four females.
#我都是一公二母 他一公四母
It's one-male-two-female at my place, but it's one-male-four-female here.
#兄弟也不夠公鼠哦
He doesn't have enough male rats too.
#看一下其他地方有沒有啦
Let me see if there is any elsewhere.
#哇 這裡有一個
Wa! Here is one!
#你看 這個公的那麼胖 也不多發兩個老婆給它
See? This male is so fat. Why didn't he give it two more wives?
#哇 超標了它
Wa! It's too fat.
#最少四斤多
At least 2kg.
#要是在我家的話 我給你發6個老婆
If you were with me, I would give you 6 wives,
#讓你的身 讓你的身材變苗條
so that your body, you can be slimmer.
#哇 好胖
Wa! Very fat!
#這個太小啦
This is too small.
#應該才兩斤
It weighs just a kilogram.
#要到3斤左右才可以
It needs to be at around 1.5 kg to
#才可以做種鼠
to breed.
#這個怎麼那麼小這個
Why is this one so small?
#這個好小 這個
This one is very small, this one.
#可能是這個搶奶 沒搶奶 沒搶夠吃
Perhaps it can't, can't fight for enough milk.
就那麼小 別人都那麼大 就它那麼小
So this is still that small. Others are that big now, but it is still so small.
才一斤左右
It weighs only about half a kilogram.
叫 叫
Squeak! Squeak!
它不叫
It doesn't squeak.
這個好小
This is very small
哎喲 哎喲 哎喲 那麼兇的這個
Aiyo, aiyo, aiyo! How fierce it is!
差點咬到我
I was almost bitten.
太猛啦
It's too fierce!
這個很老實的這個
This one is very calm.
一動不動
It is not moving at all.
僵的
Stiff
你咋啦
What happened to you?
是不是哪裡不舒服
Are you not feeling well?
要不要帶你去看一下醫生
Do you want to see a doctor?
我就是獸醫
I am a vet!
裝病
Malingering!
一放下它就跑
It ran away once I put it back.
跑到那麼遠來到兄弟家
We came all the way to my brother's,
竹鼠 他的公鼠啊 也不是很夠
only to see that he bamboo rats, his male rats, he has only barely enough.
幾乎不夠
Not even enough.
所以又白來了
So, we are leaving with empty hands again.
啊 準備回去啦
Ah! Let's get ready to go back.
你看 這個
See? This is...
跟兄弟說了一下
I have talked to my brother.
把這個帶我們的養殖廠養幾天
he agreed that I can keep this hen for a few days.
借母雞 生幾個蛋出來
I borrow his hen, for eggs.